Guide to the Charles Butler Papers 1817-1908 (Bulk 1837-1882) MC 81 MC 81
New York University Archives
Charles Butler Papers
Bulk, 1837-1882
1817-1908, (Bulk 1837-1882)
MC 81
New York University Archives
10.0 linear feet 10 linear feet (22 boxes)
Charles Butler was born in New York in 1802. He was a lawyer whose endeavors included anti-Masonry, New York politics, western state bond issues and speculation, canal, road and railroad construction, and philanthropy. The papers of Charles Butler span the years 1817 to 1908, and include correspondence, business papers, legal documents, ledger books, pamphlets, and maps.
Butler, Charles, 1802-1897
Historical/Biographical Note
During his lifetime, Charles Butler was involved in many endeavors. For a time he was employed as an agent for the New York Life Insurance and Trust Company, and held various positions in the transportation industry working with canals, roads, and railroads. He was also involved in New York politics, anti-Masonry, and state bond investment and land speculation in the antebellum west. One such interest was in the Wabash and Erie Canal, the construction of which Congress authorized in 1827. When completed in 1853, the Wabash and Erie Canal was the longest man-made waterway in the Western Hemisphere and extended nearly 500 miles. By 1860, however, after a short time in use, the canal was incrementally abandoned in response to the proliferation of railroads.
Butler's other accomplishments are outlined in the following chronology
Jan 15, 1802 Born, Kinderhook Landing, N.Y.
1819 Employed as clerk in the law office of Martin Van Buren at Albany, N.Y.
1822 Appointed deputy clerk of New York State Senate
1824 Admitted to New York Bar
1825 Married Eliza A. Ogden
1826-1827 Prosecuted the kidnappers of William Morgan, a Freemason
1829 Appointed postmaster at Geneva, N.Y.
1830 Became an agent of the New York Life Insurance and Trust Co.
1833 Traveled in Michigan, Indiana, and Illinois
1834 Moved to New York City
1836 Became a member of the Council of the University of the City of New York Became one of twenty founders of the Union Theological Seminary and a member of its first Board of Directors.
ca. 1862 President of the St. Louis, Alton, and Terre Haute Railroad Co.
1870-1897 President of the Board of Directors for the Union Theological Seminary
Dec 13, 1897 Died, New York City
Arrangement
The collection contains correspondence, business papers, legal documents, and pamphlets organized alphabetically by subject.
This collection is arranged in three series:
I. Correspondence and business papers, legal documents, and pamphlets. Arranged alphabetically by subject
II. Bound letter books and financial ledgers
III. Maps
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
New York University Council. Charles Butler papers, 1837-1899 (RG 2.0.1).
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Charles Butler span the years 1817 to 1908, the bulk of which pertain to the dealings of the American Land Company, and the Wabash and Erie Canal. They include correspondence, business papers, legal documents, ledger books, pamphlets, and maps.
Butler's American Land Company correspondence deals chiefly with property issues along the Mississippi River, public debts in Indiana, and the Wabash and Erie Canal. There is also a small amount of family correspondence and a 1833 letter written to the editor of the Albany Argus regarding travels in the western states.
The business papers include land patents for 1841, stock certificates dated 1847 and 1853, state of Michigan reports and the Governor's message of 1849, a patent signed by the secretary of the State of Wiscons in 1856, and bound letters from J.L. Williams, chief engineer of the Wabash and Erie Canal.
Many business letters are bound into volumes with indexes and prominent correspondents include Henry and Peter Anderson, Walter Goodman and James G. King of Indianapolis. Also included are legal documents which refer to the case of Anderson v. Messinger (a property case in Toledo, Ohio), correspondence, exhibits for trials in 1906 and 1908, briefs for the defendant and plaintiff, and a petition. Other legal documents concern the Wabash and Erie Canal and include letters to law offices and attorneys F.W. Gilley Jr., McDonald and Butler, F.F. Marbury, F.F. Marbury Jr. and others.
The financial ledgers contain bills receivable, bills payable, receipts, disbursements, expenses, balance sheets, and interest rates. There are also scrapbooks of newspaper clippings.
Pamphlets and annual reports span the years 1827-1878, and are primarily concerned with the Wabash and Erie Canal corporation. The maps include state maps of Pennsylvania, Indiana and Ohio from the 1840s and 50s; a detailed map of Toledo and its vicinity, with details of its streets, ports, and new additions ca. 1850s. There is also a map of an Indian Reservation and an Oak Orchard.
General note
Source: the Collection of Charles Butler, the Manuscript Division, Library of Congress.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. It is in
off-site storage
Provenance
These papers were donated to the New York University Archives by Charles Butler's daughter, Emily Ogden Butler, in 1925.
Albany Argus.; American Land Company.; Anderson, Henry, d. 1846.; Anderson, Peter, 1804-1868; Butler, Charles, 1802-1897; Butler, Emily Ogden; Croswell, Edwin, 1797-1871; Dowling, Thomas, 1806-1876; Goodman, Walter A.; Indiana. Board of Trustees of the Wabash and Erie Canal.; Williams, J. L., (Jesse Lynch), 1807-1886; Canals |x Design and construction |x Costs; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Land speculation |z United States.; Ledgers (account books).; Legal documents.; Maps.; Pamphlets.; United States |x Territorial expansion.; Wabash and Erie Canal (Ind. and Ohio)
- Series I: Correspondence, Business Papers, Legal Documents, and Pamphlets
  - American Land Company
    - American Land Company, 1837-1847 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Land Company, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Land Company, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - American Land Company, 1842-1849 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - American Land Company, 1853-1859 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - American Land Company, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Land Company, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - American Land Company, 1864-1865 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - American Land Company, 1866-1869 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - American Land Company, 1870-1875 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - American Land Company, 1877-1879 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - American Land Company, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - American Land Company, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - American Land Company, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Charles Avery File, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Charles Avery File, Jan 1883 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Charles Avery File, Feb 1883-Dec 1883 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Charles Avery File, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Charles Avery File, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Anderson v. Messinger
    - Anderson v. Messinger, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Anderson v. Messinger, 1840-1849 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Anderson v. Messinger, 1850-1859 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Anderson v. Messinger, 1860-1869 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Anderson v. Messinger, 1903-1906 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Exhibits for trial (documents dated: 1839-1866, 1906, Dec. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Exhibits for trial (documents dated: 1838-1860, Feb 13, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Briefs for the Defendant, case #679, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Briefs for the Defendant, case #11,434, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Briefs for the Defendant, case #1479, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Briefs for the Defendant, case #1879, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Briefs for the Defendant, case #1916, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Briefs for the Defendant, case #10,689, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Briefs for the Defendant, case #1679, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Briefs for the Defendant, case #1916, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Petition, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Business Correspondence
    - Business Correspondence, 1841-1845 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Business Correspondence, 1846-1849 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Business Correspondence, 1867-1868 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Business Correspondence, Jan 1869 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Business Correspondence, Feb 1869 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Business Correspondence, Mar 1869-Apr 1869 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Business Correspondence, May 1869-Jun 1869 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Business Correspondence, Jul 1869-Aug 1869 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Business Correspondence, Sep 1869-Oct 1869 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Business Correspondence, Nov 1869-Dec 1869 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Business Correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Business Correspondence. [Walter Goodman from Holly Springs, MS (bound)], 1849-1854 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Business Correspondence (bound) [Various canal related], 1850-1851 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Business Correspondence (bound), 1849-1852 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Business Correspondence (bound), 1856-1865 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Business Correspondence (bound), 1857-1860 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Business Correspondence (bound), 1860-1867 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Business Correspondence received (removed from bound vol.), 1876, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Business Correspondence received (removed from bound vol.), ca. 1828 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Business Correspondence (bound), 1833-1842 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Business Correspondence (bound), Dec 1845-May 1846 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Business Correspondence (bound), 1849 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Indiana Debt
    - Indiana Debt, 1843 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Indiana Debt, Dec 1844-Jul 1845 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Legal Documents, Jul 1845-Dec 1845 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Legal Documents, Feb 1845 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Indiana Debt, Feb 20, 1846 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Indiana Debt, Mar 1846 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Indiana Debt, Nov 1846 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Indiana Debt, Dec 1846 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Indiana Debt, 1847-1849 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - St. Joseph Valley Register, Jan 16, 1851 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - St. Joseph Valley Register, 1868 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - St. Joseph Valley Register, 1873 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Index to bound volume of letters, 1854-1856 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Index to bound volume of letters, Mar 21, 1854, -Jun. 29, 1854 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Index to bound volume of letters, Jul 10, 1854-Dec 29, 1854 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Index to bound volume of letters, Jan 1, 1855-Jun 30, 1855 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Index to bound volume of letters, Jul 1, 1855-Dec 25, 1855 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Index to bound volume of letters, Jan 2, 1856-Jun 23, 1856 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Mississippi,Indiana
    - Booklet on properties surrounding the river, ca.1835-1836 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - State of Michigan reports and Governor's Message, 1849 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Letters, declarations, and miscellaneous. Includes letter to the Albany Argus editor column about travels through several western states, 1833-1853 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Patents (land), Jan 5, 1841 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Patents (land) from the Secretary of the State of Wisconsin, Oct 3, 1856 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Wabashand Erie Canal
    - Circular Statement, 1848-1861 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1849-1858 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1862-1869 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1871-1877 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Family Correspondence, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - E.B. Allen Correspondence, 1876-1877 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - James Anderson Correspondence, 1873 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - A.L. Backus Correspondence, 1871-1876 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - J.M. Butler Correspondence, 1852-1878 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Charles J. Canda Correspondence, 1876-1877 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Edwin Croswell Correspondence, 1849-ca.1853 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - John Dowling Correspondence, 1876 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Thomas Dowling Correspondence, 1860-1874 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Thomas Dowling Correspondence, 1875-1876 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - (?) Fleetwood Correspondence, 1851-1852 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Jonathan K. Gapen Correspondence, 1868-1875 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Office of F.W. Gilley Jr. Correspondence, 1893 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - S.B. Gookins and Geo. C. Duy Correspondence, 1875-1877 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - J.H. Hager Correspondence, 1853-1877 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - J.S. Hinton Correspondence, 1875-1876 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - A. Gracie King Correspondence, ca.1853-1876 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - McDonald and Butler, Attorneys-at-Law, Office of, Correspondence, 1877-1899 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - W.R. McKeen Correspondence, 1877-1899 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - Office of F.F. Marbury and F.F. Marbury Jr. (Counselors at law) Correspondence, 1873-1887 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - D.D. Pratt Correspondence, 1869-1872 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - J.L. Williams Correspondence, 1863-1874 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - J.L. Williams Correspondence, 1875-1881 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Financial Papers, 1856-1877 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Legal Documents, 1841-1853 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Legal Documents, 1854-1872 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Legal Documents, 1873-1876, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Legal Documents: Circuit Court of the United States for the District of Indiana-in Chancery Jonathan K. Gapen vs. The Trustees of the Wabash and Erie Canal, 1875 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Legal Documents: John W. Garrett vs. Board of Trustees of Wabash and Erie Canal, Nov 11, 1872 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Memos, ca.1845-1877, undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Newspapers, 1876 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Newspapers Clippings, undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Pamphlets: Annual Reports of the Board of Trustees, 1860-1874 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Pamphlets: Memorial of the Holders of Certificates of Stock, 1857-1870 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Pamphlets: Message of..., 1865-1871 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Pamphlets: Relating to the Wabash and Erie Canal, 1827-1878 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Pamphlets: Report of the Board of Trustees, 1869-1872 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Pamphlets: Speech, 1870-1871 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Pamphlets: Miscellaneous Printed Materials, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Series II
  - Wabash and Erie Canal
    - Bound Correspondence "from Dowling, Nofsinger, Puet and others", 1849-1854 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Bound Correspondence, 1852-1856 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Stock Certificates, 1847 1853 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Bound Correspondence "from J.L. Williams, Chief Engineer and others", 1854-1859 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Bound Correspondence, 1870-1874 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Ledger Books
    - American Land Company (detailed description), 1835-1892 (Box 19)
    - Financial Volume, includes bills receivable, bills payable; with index of names, ca.1854-1861 (Box 20)
    - Financial Volume, includes receipts and disbursements, expenses, balance sheet, 1831-1840 (Box 21)
    - Wabash and Erie canal Financial volume, includes interest rates, names, who received, date, amount, when paid, 1857-1862 (Box 21)
    - Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings, 1833-1880 (Box 22)
    - Three indexed volumes, undated (Box 22)
- Series III
  - Maps (located in mapcase at rear of archives, drawer #10)
    - Northwestern Ohio, showing area of Indian reservation; inscribed "Greenville 12th Reservation mark by Gen'l Morgan (?) in 1795. Laws of 1817 for sale of 12 miles square sold in Minster, Ohio 1817, [not before 1847] (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Map of Port Lawrence and Vistula/Toledo, Aug 1834 (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Oak Orchard (properties of American Life Insurance and Trust Company, Aug 8, 1840 (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Map of Toledo and Port Lawrence Township, 1844 (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Map of Toledo and Port Lawrence Township, 1844 (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Map of Lucas Company, Feb 24, 1845 (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Indiana, 1846-1847, 1856-1857 (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - River Tracts 5&6 T.III. V.S.R. in Toledo, Ohio, Mar 1852 (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Map of Toledo showing new addition, 1872 (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Evansville, Map of Indiana and part of Ohio, undated (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Maumee River and its surroundings with Vistula Plot and Port Lawrence Plot, undated (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Mulberry, Chestnut, Elm, Lagrange, Champlain, Michigan, Ontario, Erie Streets. (Toledo), undated (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Map of Ohio, undated (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Toledo, undated (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Indiana (duplicates), 1846-1847 1856-1857 (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - The oil district Venango, Crawford and Warren Counties, Pennsylvania, 1864 (Drawer 10, Folder 1)
    - Orleans County Property, undated (Drawer 10, Folder 2)